<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Books | Kyle Thielk]]></title>
  <link href="http://kylethielk.github.io/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kylethielk.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-22T09:29:40-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kylethielk.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kyle Thielk]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[7 Habits of Highly Successful People, 96.05% Too Long.]]></title>
    <link href="http://kylethielk.github.io/blog/7-habits-of-highly-successful-people-96-05-too-long/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-23T02:55:53-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kylethielk.github.io/blog/7-habits-of-highly-successful-people-96-05-too-long</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Date Read: October 11 &ndash; 15th, 2013</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Habits-Highly-Effective-People-Powerful/dp/1455892823">Direct Amazon Link</a></p>

<p>I understand that Stephen R. Covey is highy respected and I&rsquo;m sure he rakes in $5,000+/hour consulting fees but really this book for me still falls into the &lsquo;self help&rsquo; genre where most information is common sense and that which isn&rsquo;t can be found on any &lsquo;self help&rsquo; blog for free.</p>

<p>That is not to say I do not agree with the underlying premise of each of the 7 habits. In fact Habit 1 (&ldquo;Be Proactive&rdquo;) and 5 (&ldquo;Seek first to understand, then to be understood&rdquo;) in particular I think we should all be mindful of every day. Habit 6 is titled &ldquo;Synergize&rdquo;, Habit 7 is titled &ldquo;Sharpen the Saw&rdquo;. No explanation is needed as to why &lsquo;fluff&rsquo; is the first word that comes to mind.</p>

<p>This is how I imagine Covey&rsquo;s conversation with his publisher after coming up with the idea for the book.</p>

<p>Covey: &ldquo;I have this great idea for a new book&rdquo;.
Publisher: &ldquo;Excellent, how far along in the process are you?&rdquo;
Covey: &ldquo;Finished.&rdquo;
Publisher: &ldquo;How long is it?&rdquo;
Covey: &ldquo;15 pages.&rdquo;
Publisher: &ldquo;What? We can&rsquo;t sell a 15 page pamphlet for $19.99. Fluff it up!&rdquo;</p>

<p>1 Month Later:</p>

<p>Covey: &ldquo;Ok. The book is complete. Still 15 pages of good information, but now with 365 pages of fluff as an added bonus!&rdquo;</p>

<p>Seriously read this <a href="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Seven_Habits_Study_Guide/Quick_overview_of_the_seven_habits">WikiBooks'&lsquo; summary</a>, and save yourself the time and money. Update: Even better read this <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/ericjackson/2012/07/24/the-only-thing-you-need-to-remember-about-the-seven-habits-of-highly-effective-people/">Forbes' Summary</a>.</p>

<p><em>Note: This post is part of my</em> <a href="http://www.kylethielk.com/blog/26-books-in-26-weeks/">26 Books in 26 Weeks Goal</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Enders Game, Excellent.]]></title>
    <link href="http://kylethielk.github.io/blog/enders-game-excellent/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-20T10:56:46-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kylethielk.github.io/blog/enders-game-excellent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/media/images/enders-game-cover.jpg" title="Enders Game Cover.." alt="Enders Game Cover." /></p>

<p>Date Read: September 20 &ndash; 25th, 2013</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Enders-Game-The-Ender-Quintet-ebook/dp/B003G4W49C">Direct Amazon Link</a></p>

<p>After hearing such good things about Ender&rsquo;s Game I was afraid my expectations were set too high and I would be disappointed. My general distaste for science fiction healthily balanced out the high expectations though and I ended up thoroughly enjoying it.</p>

<p>What I like about Ender&rsquo;s Game is that the science fiction complements the story and the characters, not the other way around. The story and character development comes first, science fiction is simply there to help.</p>

<p>The children in Ender&rsquo;s game are young but their opinions and thoughts are of that of someone much older. For me this was less believable than the science fiction. Adding five years to all of the characters would not minimize the effect nor would it detract from the point but would lend itself to a more credible premise. This is my one complaint.</p>

<p>The story is fantastic. It flows very well and is enjoyable the whole time. In fact I found myself wishing it was longer. I can understand why it is a book people read multiple times, I already want to read it again.</p>

<p>Definitely in my top 5 fiction books (granted that list is barely over 5, but I don&rsquo;t see it dropping out either).</p>

<p><em>Note: This post is part of my <a href="http://www.kylethielk.com/blog/26-books-in-26-weeks/">26 Books in 26 Weeks Goal</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Outliers, Thought-Provoking Storytelling.]]></title>
    <link href="http://kylethielk.github.io/blog/outliers-thought-provoking-storytelling/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-12T21:14:34-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kylethielk.github.io/blog/outliers-thought-provoking-storytelling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/media/images/outliers_cover.jpg" title="Outliers Book Cover" alt="Outliers Book Cover" /></p>

<p>Read: September 20 – 25th, 2013</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Outliers-Story-Success-Malcolm-Gladwell/dp/0316017930">Direct Amazon Link</a></p>

<p>Malcolm Gladwell is a fantastic writer and story teller. I imagine this is why his books sell so well and he has so many fans. I read Outliers in just a few days, granted it is a short book but I was also on a beach in the Philippines and I frequently had to remind myself of this fact so I didn&rsquo;t spend too much time in the room reading.</p>

<p>I was going to give the book a 5 star rating. I bought into Outliers hook line and sinker. The book basically argues that the general consensus the public and the media has of highly successful people (especially those that came form a less than favorable background) clawing and fighting themselves to the top through sheer determination and genius alone is a fallacy. Gladwell sets out to &lsquo;prove&rsquo; that it is in fact determination and hard work coupled with very fortunate circumstances and a lot of help from other people. The premise is very thought provoking and presents many case studies (read: South Korean Airlines) that are fascinating.</p>

<p>As a quick example Gladwell points out that in the world of Canadian Hockey, a large percentage of the elite players were born in the same few months. As children this meant they were older than their peers in the same leagues and thus more developed and larger. This small advantage when younger is quickly magnified as the better players receive more training and attention. This ties into Gladwell&rsquo;s 10,000 hour theory then; since the players receive more training and attention, they reach the 10,000 hour mark much quicker and thus become the &lsquo;elite&rsquo; players. The elite players are the elite because of one small advantage as a child that creates a snowball effect throughout their life.</p>

<p>I was a little behind with this book summary, I&rsquo;m writing it a few weeks after finishing the book. The other day I completely by chance stumbled upon an article by Paul Raeburn on MIT&rsquo;s Science Journal: <a href="http://ksj.mit.edu/tracker/2013/10/should-we-stop-believing-malcolm-gladwel">Should we stop believing Malcolm Gladwell</a> and this follow-up: <a href="http://ksj.mit.edu/tracker/2013/10/malcolm-gladwell-speaks-can-narrative-be">Malcolm Gladwell speaks: Can narrative be misused in journalism?</a></p>

<blockquote>"I am a story-teller, and I look to academic research … for ways of augmenting story-telling. ...we’re obsessed with things like coherence, consistency, neatness of argument. Readers are indifferent to those things." -Malcolm Gladwell

"All writing about social science need not be presented with the formality and precision of the academic world. There is a place for storytelling, in all of its messiness." -Malcolm Gladwell</blockquote>


<p>Gladwell absolutely presents his work in Outliers as fact, as well-researched and verified fact (which I assume he does in his other books as well). These comments from Gladwell himself seem to directly contradict this. They leave me feeling slightly betrayed. Gladwell&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/health_and_science/science/2013/10/malcolm_gladwell_s_david_and_goliath_he_explains_why_christopher_chabris.html">response to these criticisms</a> does absolutely nothing to disprove his critics and simply tells them to &ldquo;calm down&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Outliers must be taken as a story, a very good story. Do not take it as well researched journalism or fact even if it is presented that way and you will be much better for it.</p>

<p><em>Note: This post is part of my <a href="http://www.kylethielk.com/blog/26-books-in-26-weeks/">26 Books in 26 Weeks Goal</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Stand, Brilliant...Long.]]></title>
    <link href="http://kylethielk.github.io/blog/the-stand-brilliant-long/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-11T09:58:16-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kylethielk.github.io/blog/the-stand-brilliant-long</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/media/images/The_Stand_cover.jpg" title="The Stand Cover" alt="The Stand Cover" />
Read: September 2 &ndash; 20th, 2013</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Stand-Stephen-King/dp/0307947300/">Direct Amazon Link</a></p>

<p>I have always wanted to read a Stephen King book and now that I&rsquo;ve committed myself to reading <a href="http://www.kylethielk.com/blog/26-books-in-26-weeks/">26 books in 26 weeks</a>, there could not not be a better time.  Stephen King&rsquo;s collection of works is quite large and with very little prior knowledge of any of them I simply chose the one that appeared to be the most popular, The Stand.</p>

<p>The fact that it is over 800 pages is a little intimidating. In fact I attempted to read the first Game of Thrones book which is similar in length and only made it 60% of the way through.  Fortunately the number of characters and story lines that the reader must keep straight is far more manageable in The Stand. Game of Thrones is just far too difficult to read unless done so in a near continuous span of time.</p>

<p>Stephen King&rsquo;s style of writing in The Stand is simple but descriptive. I found the story intriguing and the way in which the character&rsquo;s stories were wound together made it that much easier to read and thus enjoy. I never once found myself bored or at risk of  losing interest. There were multiple times that I had to force myself to take a break.</p>

<p>A minor complaint with the book is that there are a few major questions left unanswered. The supernatural aspects of the story are never really presented with a cause or explanation.  They simply happen and we have to accept them.</p>

<p>In order to maintain a level of variety (and ensure I can actually finish 26 books by the end of the year) I will probably not include another Stephen King novel in the list as much as I would like to.  I do however plan on picking up more of them for pleasure after this project is complete.</p>

<p><em>Note: This post is part of my <a href="http://www.kylethielk.com/blog/26-books-in-26-weeks/">26 Books in 26 Weeks Goal</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Life of Pi, Ups and Downs]]></title>
    <link href="http://kylethielk.github.io/blog/life-of-pi-ups-and-downs/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-02T12:34:12-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kylethielk.github.io/blog/life-of-pi-ups-and-downs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.kylethielk.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/life-of-pi-book-cover.jpg" title="Life of Pi Book Cover" alt="Life of Pi Book Cover" /></p>

<p>Read: Jul 30 &ndash; August 24, 2013</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Life-Pi-Yann-Martel/dp/0547848412">Direct Amazon Link</a></p>

<p>Life of Pi is a quick read. Life of Pi took me 25 days to read, an average of 14.24 pages a day. It certainly put a damper on my attempt to read 26 books in 26 weeks (that and I&rsquo;m currently reading the 800+ page &ldquo;The Stand&rdquo; by Stephen King) and I now have a lot of ground to make up. This was a particularly busy month (excuses, excuses) but the point is when I could actually make time the book was easy to get through and the total time to finish the book is not at all indicative of the time spent actually reading. There are very few characters and only one plot line to follow so very little cognitive power is required.</p>

<p>Life of PI starts off well. Pi walks us through his various encounters with Hinduism, Christianity and Islam and his attempts to be all three at once. His family dynamics and the various lessons he learns from them as well, which quickly and nicely set the stage for the meat of the book.</p>

<p>The majority of the book takes place on PI&rsquo;s lifeboat with his tiger shipmate, Richard Parker. At first the struggle to survive is enthralling, I didn&rsquo;t want to stop reading. Unfortuately it drags on, and on. I found myself losing interest fairly quickly. There were a few bright spots that brought me back in (the floating island), but mostly I was looking forward to the end.</p>

<p>The end comes and finishes off the story nicely. Its a story of hope and it makes you feel good despite the not so pleasant circumstances. So even though I lost interest the ending &lsquo;sort of&rsquo; saves the book.</p>

<p>I watched the movie the day after completing the book (which is actually the first time I&rsquo;ve ever read a book first). My recommendation is to watch it and skip the book. The movie is visually stunning and does an excellent job of condensing the book into a 2 hour film.</p>

<p><em>Note: This post is part of my</em> <a href="http://www.kylethielk.com/blog/26-books-in-26-weeks/">26 Books in 26 Weeks Goal</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
